welcome to the official ronnie landis
podcast show
where you learn to upgrade the human
experience through natural nutrition
lifestyle design and consciousness
engineering this is no ordinary health
or personal growth podcast
and ronnie landis is definitely no
ordinary host
ronnie landis is an integrative
nutritionist transformation coach
and human behavioral specialist he
brings on some of the world's leading
thought leaders
to deliver to you the most cutting edge
information and unique perspectives
so you can create the life of your
dreams get ready to receive your upgrade
in all you believed was possible
starting now greetings everyone
welcome to another edition of the
official ronnie landis podcast show
i am of course your host ronnie landis
before we dive into today's epic
incredible
mind-altering mind expanding interview
with our guest
daniel schmockenberger i want to drive a
little bit of your attention
to one of my favorite cognitive
enhancing
brain boosting neuroprotective
products that i've ever come across we
sometimes call these products
nootropics which are defined by either
helping increase vasodilation which is
blood flow to the brain
or increasing nerve growth factors which
have implications in increasing
white matter or glial cell production in
the brain
which we're coming to find out is
actually most of what makes a healthy
brain
and what helps create that neuro
neurological
syndication of communication networks in
the brain
via what are called glial cells and
microglial cells
and nerve growth factors which have to
do with the myelination
of our nerves of our of our nervous
system
and memory short-term long-term memory
all that kind of cool stuff that you can
nerd out on for
hours on end like i do there's an
incredible product that i started
playing with
um about about a month and a half ago
and this product is called qualia and i
have to say
qualia has been qualified in my opinion
as the best nootropic product i have
ever
experimented with in my life literally
the first time i tried it
it immediately balanced my mental
emotional coherence
i felt throughout the day more emotional
um resilience i felt more mental clarity
more mental endurance like i could go
through my entire day
with a level of cognitive cl um
uh what's the word not just not just um
almost like clairvoyance is an
interesting word that's coming to mind
but it's just clarity and and mental
endurance
where i didn't run out of mental
bandwidth i could
process things quicker and make those
those
synaptic connections much quicker
sometimes we call that synaptogenesis
that's another interesting term that you
can geek out on as well
and i'm not making any claims about it
but giving my experience and the
experience of so
many people that i have talked to about
this product
it is by far the best thing i've ever
come across
it is my favorite supplement by far the
product
is called qualia and it's by a company
called
neurohacker and i
will invite you to go to neurohacker.com
look at the research behind the product
look and kind of investigate
a little bit and if it resonates with
you and you want to experiment with it
you can actually use the coupon code
human potential which is my coupon code
human potential and you will receive 10
off your first order and you
i believe will be very um
shockingly surprised at the positive
effects
not only in the short term but the long
term enduring positive effects that take
place
from this product that's my experience
that's been the experience of many many
other people
and i invite you to have an experience
as well
so let's move on with the interview
speaking of neurohacker the founder of
neurohacker collective
daniel schmockenberger is our guest
today
and i have to say daniel is one of the
most
impressive polymaths that i have come
across
polymath is a term to describe somebody
that has achieved multi-disciplinary
mastery meaning a level of mastery
in a multitude of disciplines
and daniel's just a really fun guy to
talk to he's a very humble
grounded down to earth and very
um brilliant human being to say the
least and you'll you'll get that sense
when you're listening to this
conversation
this conversation goes in a plethora of
directions
and it would almost be a disservice to
even try to explain this interview
just in a quick little snippet what i
will say
is that don't try to
absorb everything right away the way
that daniel's
mind works is like in a holographic
nature that's why
that's why i felt that we could really
have an incredible conversation together
because
my brain tends to work holographically
meaning that i
can see multiple subjects or multiple
things in a constellation
almost holographically projected in
front of me
and i know a lot of you listening to
this have relayed similar experiences
which is probably why a lot of you
feel called towards my speaking style
and feel called towards the guests that
i bring on
because i only bring on people that i am
impressed by that i support their work
and that
i actually genuinely want to have a
conversation with
otherwise i'm not going to bring them on
i'm not going to waste
their time my time or your time and
man was this was this um just an
incredible download and transmission
wow i'm actually going to refrain from
trying to describe
this interview in any more detail i
really just want to invite you to have
your own experience
and kind of get the downloads and
insights that come
to you so without further ado
that's it from me let's bring on uh
daniel schmuckenberger and enjoy this
conversation
immensely
[Music]
daniel is the director of research and
development and a co-founder at
neurohacker collective
where he is focused on developing
processes and technologies for advancing
medicine and human optimization
he is particularly focused on
personalized medicine
adequate approaches to complex illness
and deepening our knowledge of how the
human regulatory systems
function how they break down and how
they can be supported to function with
greater
resilience welcome to the show
thanks for having me ron good to be here
yeah it's uh
i feel like it's been a long time coming
even though you and me just started
really connecting um more personally as
of recently
you've been on my radar for quite some
time within the collective community
that we come from in uh northern san
diego
um however the more i go down the rabbit
hole as these things tend to
tend to happen the more people around
the country around the
the even around the planet now no of you
know of your work know of your products
um qualia which has just kind of
accumulated on my radar until i finally
started playing with it
which i have to say um i know we'll dive
more into
that product and the work there you're
doing with neurohacker collective but i
have to just say
as we start out here that is my single
favorite uh cognitive enhancement
product that i've ever tried
and um yeah i'm looking forward to
diving into
that as well as all the other
interesting territory that we're going
to cover today
sounds fun cool so the first place that
i'd love to start
is the origin story which
i've i've dug into a little bit of yours
just from
certain podcasts that you've given and i
have to say that
you have a very unique and novel
upbringing comparatively
to you know most people's upbringing i
would imagine
and so maybe you could just share some
of your your background
and the upbringing you had
uh sure so the
novel upbringing uh i'm imagining you
mean i was uh
i was homeschooled growing up and i was
homeschooled by
uh really thoughtful parents who uh
had ideas about educational philosophy
and how
uh childbearing and human naturalization
could work
and want to experiment on their kids
which was cool
and so our home school was set up
with no curriculum at all no fixed
curriculum so we did no
social studies math english etc
that were curriculum-based the idea
instead which
is become more popular recently with uh
things like
unschooling um the approach that we had
was so a little different
it was to expose us to as much as
possible to see what we were interested
in and then facilitate those interests
as fully as possible and so topics that
i didn't express
interest in i never really learned and
so
i i didn't learn much about
american history as a child because it
wasn't an area where my interest was
naturally peaked
and i never learned state capitals and
et cetera my i didn't learn much in the
way of spelling my handwriting never got
legible
um but i did go deep in
uh most of the sciences very early and
then most of the philosophic traditions
and in many areas of activism and that
was kind of the braid
that all my interests fit into and the
the kind of uh educational philosophy
idea
was that kids are intrinsically
interested
curious that there was evolutionary
benefit to being curious being
fascinated and that if we
facilitate their fascination not only do
they become
uh masterful at things because they put
a lot of cycles
of earnest attention and energy because
they're intrinsically motivated
but their interest in life continues to
develop passion life is developed that
when you don't facilitate kids interests
and you try to force them to do shit
that they're not interested in
that's how you kind of break people's
interests in life and they just want a
bad job and watch tv
and so that ended up being true
uh in my case and um
one of the things that was real
interesting was since i didn't have
specific subjects there was no division
between
biology chemistry physics philosophy so
it was
an inquiry into the nature of something
and asking
why that is enough times usually led you
know a trip around the universe asking
questions about why plants grew that led
to
soil biology that led to microbiology
that led to understanding what the
minerals were and how they were
formed in supernovas and that meant uh
you know astrophysics and
cosmology got into
uh relativity and modern physics and you
know et cetera so
uh that led to not only kind of a
study across a lot of areas but the
relationship between those areas so
interdisciplinary science
but more than that system science and
the deeper philosophy of
why does universe work the way that it
does across
all of those different domains which is
where the underpinning was really in
a philosophic system so that was a
little bit about the background and
uh you know my dad was largely
uh interested in science and philosophy
so i got a lot of support there my mom
was interested in the arts and the
humanities and activism
and so as far as exposure goes she took
me to
work with greenpeace and peta and
embassy international and you know
those kinds of things early and so
the impulse was from earliest on i can
remember and i
i see this impulse in all the kids that
i interact with and it'll express in
totally unique ways and
my brother expressed very differently
but but the impulse was the same was to
understand the nature of the reality we
live in
to understand what is ultimately
meaningful and to see
how we can uniquely contribute to it in
the way that is
you know most meaningful for us
so that's a little bit about the
childhood part
and who are some of your mentors
that you paid attention to during your
upbringing and as your curiosity and
fascination
on all these different subject matter
grew
who are some of the people that come
that's that kind of come to your mind
immediately that played a big
role in your your kind of fascination
there were people that i actually
physically met who were mentors
but early on the kind of deepest
influences were
just the uh the philosophers scientists
teachers that i was fascinated by and
that
got to be the basis of my curriculum so
the
first name that comes to mind is being
the probably the most significant early
intellectual influence for me was about
mr fuller
and as one of my dad's great heroes uh
bucky's work was my probably most common
early bedtime story as a kid even
before i was verbal and one of the
things is it's like as hard as it might
seem for us as adults to learn
a new language and especially a very
different language say mandarin
uh baby who grows up hearing it learns
it no problem
well in the same way if we grow up
hearing the kinds of words that are in
children's books we'll learn those if we
grow up hearing different kinds of words
we'll learn those
just as easily and so
you know my early words had a lot to do
with synergetic geometry and integrity
and because that's what i was exposed to
and um so above mr fuller
and design science and specifically
looking at how to
design technology that is both modeled
after how nature works and that
intentionally works
in in alignment with
complex adaptive systems core part of my
early childhood development and then a
lot of the
systems thinkers advance in popularized
systems thinking so frichoff capra
irvin laszlo the people who developed
auto poesis theory self-organization
complex adaptive systems
stuart kaufman all those kind of guys
you know obviously the bit of tv that
came in was
cosmos and carl sagan
that and um you know in the eastern
traditions were very deep
for me so i
got to live in the in fairfield iowa in
the transcendental meditation community
for
the first six years of life and so
uh marishi mahashogi the kind of
one of the people that brought eastern
philosophy to the
west he was a meaningful early influence
and that then led to lots of eastern
philosophy
um western philosophy came a little bit
after that
and then you know the great activists
gandhi was a very deep
and profound early influence
are many many examples but uh i was i
was fortunate to
have examples of great role models
yeah i really and i really appreciate
what you're sharing about the natural
curiosity and fascination that children
have with
learning and one of the things that i
really feel like i've been a voice for
just in the subtle realms of my work
maybe when i go off on tangents or
something or i'm working with parents
in particular i tend to really
focus in on a child's innate well not
even just children but people's innate
tendencies what are they naturally
gravitating towards
and if they are given i guess i don't
know the permission slip or they're
given encouragement to pursue those
things
their intrinsic genius starts to kind of
come about where
you know for example our our industrial
education system doesn't
foster that type of environment right
it's just kind of rinse repeat memorize
um and you know focus on the end result
being a grade on your paper
and so i feel as though this
conversation is really important
and just for just to maybe plant a seed
in people's mind that
that whatever whatever we're naturally
curious
about is is leading us towards our
intrinsic genius does that does that
sound about right to you yeah so
to just kind of um piggyback on that a
little bit
so the extension beyond childhood and
homeschool for me was
when i started college and again i was
well facilitated so i was fortunate to
get to uh start college in the
university
young um i had no intention of getting
degrees and i had no idea what i planned
on
doing with any of the knowledge and kind
of vocation sense i knew i was
interested in
understanding reality and being
empowered by that to
help shape civilization but i didn't
know what that looked like yet i didn't
know enough so
i got into mathematics and it was just
i was just passionate about
understanding how these
maximally abstracted principles of order
and relationship work
and so i just dove into mathematics and
um
you know had all math classes at the
same time
and my you know my parents
did ask you so do you want to be a
mathematician
i just i wasn't thinking that way at all
i was thinking
that there was deep innate fascination
for me and understanding this and
at a certain point uh i
by no means understood all that one
could understand in mathematics which
isn't even possible but uh but i got to
a place where i
understood math well enough
that what the impulse that was driving
me there had found a certain kind of
completion it wasn't
uh it wasn't actually just to work in
math it was to understand
how to think through induction and
deduction and formal logic and
abstraction and
uh you know et cetera to understand the
language that the sciences operated in
and as soon as that happened my
attention moved my fascination was in
physics and then all of my attention was
just kind of deep diving and then
it moved to uh vedantic philosophy
moved to medicine and moved to ecology
and um
some people could think that that was
lack of focus and it was so clearly not
to me
it was it was
following a kind of natural process
that i wasn't crystal clear on i knew
was trending towards
accumulating the skills and capacities
and insights
necessary to do what was going to be
mine to do even though i didn't know
exactly what that was
but pretty much as soon as an area would
reach a completion of what i needed to
do with it in my opinion moved to the
next thing
until there was an adequate body of
capacities that i could
actually put together what was really
mine to do which had to do with
whole systems design at the level of
civilization how do we
uh fundamentally redesign the core
axioms of civilization was a feature of
macroeconomics
post-capitalism look like that has
uh incentives that
don't externalize harm what is the
future of governance that has adequate
decision-making capacity to the scope of
decisions that we have to make in the
future look like as a future
infrastructure look like
my focus was a whole system civilization
design and even though i intuited that i
couldn't have said that
but it actually needed the skills of all
of those things that i worked in
so there was a deeper than conscious
process guiding that
it was pretty much what my fascination
was and so being allowed to follow that
was a gift
that i uh wish for everyone
yeah yeah very well explained and that's
exactly
what i wish for everyone too and it's
funny what you mentioned about kind of
the hopscotching model of
self-interest based education because
when i look back on my life it's very
much
the same thing i was raised as a martial
artist
which caused me to be intimately exposed
to
eastern philosophy and and many
different modalities in that world and
then eventually
you know the last i would say eight or
nine years i've been more interested in
science and then
learning the language of science or
different formats of science
um for example where growing up that
wasn't something that i was interested
in so in my i naturally didn't have a
proclivity towards it so therefore i
didn't apply myself
and teachers probably assumed that um i
don't think i was ever assumed like
quote unquote
dumb i was just like maybe i was assumed
just really bored or like all i wanted
to do was
go on a track and field and run or work
out or something
um however i do realize though as i got
older the link between this subject
matter being different forms of science
and things that i previously was not
interested in the link between that and
my purpose
now had been created therefore
you know that now there's more of a
natural proclivity to apply myself
because now i see how that matches up
with what i believe that i'm here to do
on the earth so
i think that's really fascinating um
and i want to use this as a segway i
really love what you're sharing i want
to use this as a segue to go into some
of the principles that you
share in some of your talks to further
expand upon
just kind of what what your philosophy
or the philosophy that i think you're
working from is about
so maybe we can give the audience a
basic foundational understanding on
your perspectives around the principles
of emergence and omni consideration
sure uh great topics
so
omni consideration is
as inclusive a word
as i can think of
for uh if we have to kind of bring it to
us
a single word core value or guiding
principle
only consideration is the closest that i
could get which is how do we
think about everything that is affected
and impacted by an
any decision and how do we care so how
do we care about it
and then think through the actual
causation well
and factor the well-being of everything
that is affected in every choice made
and so you know
why would that even be relevant well
it's relevant when
we recognize the first step of relevance
is when we recognize that we live in
an interconnected universe that on our
biosphere we live in a very
interconnected biosphere
that our technology is big enough that
we're affecting things across the whole
biosphere in real time we're making
purchases that are
affecting supply chains on you know most
of the continents
um and that
there there really is no such thing as a
way wherever our trash goes there really
is no such thing as others where however
their quality of life is being affected
it's leading to their patterns of
behaviors leading to how they're
affecting the oceans the ecosystems that
are
that we're all fundamentally
interconnected with and so
pre-industrial revolution when there was
less than a half a billion people and we
didn't have much technology
there's a different set of rules in that
evolutionary environment for
it was possible to have win lose games
it wasn't a good idea but it was
possible and we did that so
resource issues one tribe could kill
another tribe to have access to the
resource
and you know that that could work when
you get to the level of
technology where we're at now where
you know it went from we have conflict
and
uh if we can't figure it out we'll kill
each other and we're using stones
and then we're using spears then we're
using bow and arrows and we're using
guns and we're using missiles
as soon as we're dealing with uh you
know nuclear weapons weapons of mass
destruction
are our weapons are actually bigger than
the playing field can manage
and the wars are not winnable when we're
cutting down
trees unrenewably but there's just not
that many of us will came down with an
axe it's one thing when we're slashing
burning an acre a second it's a
different thing right
and so we've got the resource per capita
utilization we have now
times seven billion people the same way
of let's
you know when at the expense of the
environment or when at the expense of
each other
well at the expense of the environment
means now
the life support system of the planet
can't continue to support us and we
don't exist and at the expense of each
other means unwinnable wars
we've basically got a level of power
that has obsoleted when we lose games
being possible
anymore they're not even possible so now
we can continue to try
and have lose-lose gains or we have to
switch to fundamentally win-win games
which are not
zero sum which are fundamentally
positive sum
and this is just a totally different uh
set of behavioral mechanics set of
thought processes
dynamics so omni consider it you know
part of the driver is
we actually don't continue as a species
without moving into omni consideration
because if we don't contemplate
the welfare of the ocean so we continue
to do
agriculture in a way that has nitrogen
runoff lead to growing dead zones in the
oceans
and continue to do carbon emissions in a
way that leads to ocean acidification
and warming kills the coral
we don't keep existing right if we
continue to do fishing in a way that
overfishes
the populations and so this is a key
concept
is we are used to
in modern times and the west
specifically
thinking of ourselves as individuals and
so i can think of me as if that's a
separateable
concept and that i can think about my
own success
uh separate from the success of
everything else
well it's important to get that's
actually a nonsense
concept it seems like it's a meaningful
concept
but the only reason that i can think
about me at all is because there's a
biosphere that allows me to exist
and i just have to take that for granted
and say well of course there's a
biosphere let's talk about me
if there's no biosphere there's no meat
right so without
oxygen i don't mean much without the
plants that make the oxygen i don't mean
much without the
soil microbes that make the plants
possible make the oxygen without all of
the people that have come before me that
have created the technology that i
utilized that created the language that
creates the linguistic structure of
thought through which i think and
perceive the world
the me that i think of as me wouldn't
exist at all and so i get
i'm actually not separate from all of
that i'm not an individual
i'm an emergent property of the whole
and as soon as i get that i am i as an
individual is actually just a bad
thought that is a misnomer right it's
not understanding the dynamics well
then the idea of separate interest just
becomes nonsense
because if i don't exist without plants
me damaging plants to advantage my
existence
doesn't make that much sense right and
especially as we get to the point where
we've damaged plants enough
that we are close to tipping points of
it not just being a bad idea but it
being an existential idea
and so um omni consideration
is actually requisite
for our continued survival as a species
this is this is a big deal you know we
think of
jesus or buddha like characters that we
would say kind of had this omni
consideration of
character welfare of all sentient beings
but they were extreme outliers as we
move to the place
where exponential technology is
increasing
the impact that all humans can have and
it's increasing it exponentially
how can we continue to have
exponentially more
impact without having exponentially
better choice making
and continue to make it or we don't
and so we are our choice making being
omnipotent
which would be the result of it being
omni consider it right thinking
if we consider a process could lead to
omnipositive results
in a world that is this uh
interconnected
and with this much scope of impact
that is actually the only way to
continue making it so
this is a big deal because what we're
saying is in the face of
in the face of population and in the
face of more specifically exponential
technology
it's as if you know we can use the
metaphor that we are merging into having
the power of gods
well the power of gods you
better have the wisdom and the love and
the discernment of gods or you
self-destruct yes
and so exponential technology
necessitates
that omni-considerate humans
become the new normal in the next very
short period of time
that's like that's like human beings 3.0
that's like the the next logical and
necessary
upgrade to the humanoid template which
we currently
are are experiencing however whatever
your perspective is spiritually
whether we're just souls carting around
is in this this meat suit or this
avatar-like vessel or whatever the
particular perspective is the reality is
that we need to go
through some sort of quantum
leap evolutionary process within
this generation um which is in it maybe
it's just a consciousness upgrade that
that ripples throughout the whole system
um which is this omni consideration
model
versus this self-consideration this this
um
self-centric model in which and which i
think we've largely been conditioned
with right because when somebody
you know as a biological symbiotic kind
of organism
um the the the
uh what's the word i'm trying to find
it's the program or the tendency is
cooperation right it's not competition
it's not survival of the fittest it's
adaptability and cooperation so
naturally we want to work together
naturally we want
we want the best welfare for all
for for everyone and all creatures
however it just seems to me that we have
been culturally conditioned
to focus on ourself because of the
illusion or
maybe not so much the illusion in some
cases of scarcity
so let's let's think about the narrative
of how we got here and i'm going to
radically oversimplify it
to just share one of the causal through
lines
so say we go to uh
shortly after the plow and agriculture
and early civilizations and they they
differentiated in different ways as we
would see people do and
you know cultures do today we'd expect
and for whatever reasons environmental
reasons and etc
you had some cultures that were more
focused
on the arts and the humanities and
spiritual traditions and less focused on
um militaries and expanding their
territory and you had other ones that
were focused on the other side of that
and you can imagine it was a natural
gradient of those
possibilities for a number of reasons
and so we see
uh history of uh you know we see
archaeology of matrifocal
matriarchal societies that had less
violence that were more peace-loving as
a result they invested less in their
militaries and more in their arts
and then whenever a militarized culture
met a more peaceful culture they killed
the peaceful culture and took their
stuff
and became and then applied their stuff
to their increased militarized capacity
and continued on and then when a couple
violent militarized cultures met the
more successful one on a battlefield won
and again assimilated the stuff of the
other ones and continued and so
there was a natural selection that
occurred
but it was a natural selection of
dominance capacity
one in war and one and economic
competition and again economic
competition ended up meaning
uh how quickly we could extract
resources from the ecosystem
regardless of how whether they were
regenerating or not
and so we'd have more economic capacity
if we could pull
uh grains out even if it was divert
diverse desertifying soil or if we could
pull out coal or oil depending upon the
time period we were at
and so what that means is because nature
didn't have a balance sheet the better
that we raped the environment and
externalized harm to it the more
industrious we were and so the better
that we
competed in the free market and the
better we competed at war the better we
did in that way
so there was this kind of natural
selection of
effective cooperation of an in-group in
its competition with all-out group which
meant
its effective dominance capacity
and so
we can see how we got here that way
but that wasn't a conscious selection
of what is actually going to be
enduringly sustainable and viable or
that was true good and beautiful into
the future
it was a unconscious selection
of what had dominance capacity
now and
as we continue where our ability to
extract resources from the environment
has hit tipping points of
moving past peak resource on a bunch of
key resources
we can't continue with that success
strategy we're almost out of the ability
to do that with many
areas which means you've got an
exponential curve up and then you hit a
cliff and then it drops off
um you know we went from half a billion
people for
all of hominid history before the
industrial revolution and the industrial
revolution's ability to extract
resources from the earth much faster
we've gone to
you know almost 7.2 billion people in
the blink of an eye
and that population increase was not
based on
renewable resource utilization but
extraction of planetary savings accounts
that we're not renewing
and so again you when you hit the
tipping point then you get
uh extreme drop off and we're right
there or you get
some fundamental civilization
restructuring which we can talk about
and so you know that has been the
selection criteria
and what's interesting is we can't
continue
resource extraction or harm
externalization to the environment like
we've done and we can't continue to win
wars where our technological capacity in
military
is too big for any war to be winnable
and so what is
how we've dealt with these things for
all of civilization since agriculture
till now
is not a way we can continue to deal
with it so we're looking at a phase
shift for civilization that is deeper
than anything we have in all of recorded
history
and this is a big deal
this is a big deal for us to get one of
the things that's so interesting is that
when we think about evolution as this
kind of algorithmic process of what ends
up being adaptive now in an environment
but that leads to increased orderly
complexity
we get the orderly complexity of
prefrontal courtesies in humans and
now with all the information we have
where we actually have the capacity with
abstraction to think about things like
evolution itself
and where it's trending and have the
capacity for omni consideration
where rather than just being part of a
big evolutionary dynamic we can actually
choose to participate with the evolution
of the whole we can become stewards of
the evolution of the whole
and not just focus on what's adapted now
but what is
a true and good and beautiful feature
that we're interested in creating
and i would say this is one way to think
about the phase shift
is a phase shift from unconscious
algorithmic evolution of what's adapted
now based on dominance
to a conscious evolution
mediated by conscious agents
that factors a forecasted future of the
true the good and the beautiful
for everyone right that's normally
considerate and sustainable regenerative
et cetera
and so evolution itself is evolving to
being a more consciously agentically
mediated process where we become
stewards of evolution
i think this is a key way of thinking
about the phase transition
right now yeah yeah absolutely i
um what comes to mind is the
the famous book the holographic universe
did you ever read that book by michael
tabbit
talbot yeah what do you what do you
think about that idea because
everything i hear i kind of maybe it's
because i have my own cognitive bias
because i'm i'm redirecting certain
concepts back into a holographic
perspective
when i hear things like emergence when i
hear macro and micro when i hear omni
consideration which to me
translates into the fact that our
thoughts words and deeds affect the
whole
um here's what what's your you know
what's your perspective on that whole
thing
there are patterns of self-similarity
at all scales uh
holograms are one way of thinking about
self-similarity
uh and fractals are another way
um things like the constructal law or
other ways of
looking at you know branching dynamics
whether it's a cardiovascular system or
a river network or
a tree root network so we see patterns
of
kind of similar structures
across scale and across areas because
they have to do with deep structures and
the nature of reality
so as far as this goes we look at
a holographic on the scale of what is in
the highest good of
a person and what's in the highest good
of
all people and what's in the highest
good of all life when you factor all the
cause and effect
feedback loops will always be the same
thing
it might seem like it's possible to
benefit yourself at the expense of
somebody else or the expense of your
future self
that's only because you're not factoring
some of the cause and effect feedback
loops of wherever you externalize
harm actually as you continue to follow
where that harm goes will come back to
affect you right
when you factor all of it it's kind of
like you know cancer cells
start having their own agency
their own kind of process of growth and
development
be decoupled from their relationship
with all the other cells around them and
then that result
is if they're successful and they kill
the body then they die too
and so it actually doesn't end up being
a net good deal for them right
but it happened because they were
damaged right some radical oxidative
damage occurred and so
they lost some meaningful capacity for
self-regulation
and right now we can think about humans
uh you know
at the level of nations at the level of
corporations at the level of individual
humans
lacking some of the capacities necessary
to regulate
and make choices in a way that is good
for them in the whole simultaneously and
the development of those capacities is
key to what we need to be doing
[Music]
so this is a good opportunity for me to
switch into this
lane which is um well i would just love
actually just to dive into your personal
views on vegetarianism and veganism as
lifestyle models as our collective
population
moves more into a conscious awareness of
sentience
and moves away from a culture that seems
to be so heavily invested in its own
demise
how do you see things like vegetarianism
and veganism as
models fitting into that
um super important deep
complex difficult question yeah
um i i want to say this because
i don't want to handle the topic without
the nuance that it deserves
it's very easy to say vegetarianism and
veganism is a comprehensively better way
because of the ethics of
[Music]
the you know how we relate to other
sentient beings
because of the environmental load and
impact of
factory farming or in general converting
plant biomatter to animal biomatter
does it you know there's a those
arguments are easy to make and i'm
compelled
by all of them i i saw a
factory farm slaughter truck as a little
kid saw animals that were in
gruesome conditions was horrified by it
had always loved animals and loved meat
without really realizing how those
chicken
together that well growing up like most
people and
did a deep dive right then read john
robbins diet for new america
got into pita and then you know
vegetarianism and
animal activism and you know became a
deep part of my life focus
that said the critiques
that the you know the book the
vegetarian myth and the critiques
that you know the people in the paleo
world and uh etc will give
some of them are also meaningful and
well-founded and
uh so i i want to address
is it just about plant-based versus
animal-based uh no of course not the
argument that
if people are eating uh sustainably
grown
organic mixed farm uh animal protein
compared to conventional agriculture
that is
you know plant-based food that is you
know pouring glyphosate into the
atmosphere and destroying uh ecosystems
for row crop
then arguably the animal agriculture is
both more
you know sustainable and actually maybe
even kills less net animals than what it
took to make that agricultural space
this is totally true
is it uh true that for some people being
healthy
is easier with certain animal products
in their diet
this is definitely true for many people
uh being vegetarian is actually easier
to be healthy
um but for some people for various
reasons
uh whether it has to do with um amino
acids
fatty acids uh heme iron uh etc some
people actually have a much harder time
being healthy on a vegetarian especially
vegan diet especially if they don't know
how well
and so then we deal with the ethics of
their own kind of suffering so
i just want to say that i think the
topic is really
important and warrants uh
nuance in its handling i think there are
core axioms of the whole conversation
that are about to change
because i think um manufactured meat
stem cell
generated meat is going to be a
game-changing technology
uh where we
people who for um health reasons
that they feel that they need it or for
taste reasons or for whatever
want to eat uh animal protein
would have the ability to do that
without the environmental implications
of
traditional animal agriculture and
without
the ethical implications of something
that ever had a nervous system
and where the energy input
per kilo of meat generated is actually
profoundly low
obviously there's a lot of work to do to
dial in the micro nutrition of it
but the combination of that with better
uh
you know aeroponics and other
agriculture
method for plant matter i think is
necessary to be able to feed
all of the world's people renewably
healthfully um
whether someone ultimately at this point
ends up choosing to include some
animals in their diet whether they say
okay i'm cool with fish but not above or
i'm cool with
you know even peter singer was in the
conversation about should we be cool
with oysters and clams and mussels the
vibe
by valve creatures because there's you
know argument around do they feel
do they feel pain um does it have
and how do we know does it do insects
you know cricket flower
cricket flower you can actually produce
a whole lot of protein
and with a small amount of energy you
know per acre which has a lot of
environmental benefits
but do do they feel pain do we know is
it is it based on nerves is it based on
opiate receptors is it based on
movement dynamics so i would say there
are ethically deep questions here
and they are being explored and they
should be explored so other people
decide that they
don't eat any animal products at all or
they will eat
non-kale animal products so they'll eat
kill things below the certain level of
nervous system development they feel
good with and you ask questions like
well what about fungus fungus isn't the
plant or an animal what about
you know or they decide that they are
comfortable with mammals so long as they
hunt them or wherever they decide to be
with it
thinking through it and feeling through
it deeply for their
own ethical alignment is key
and um i don't think anyone can think
and feel through it deeply
and decide that they feel good about the
ethics of factory farms
i don't that's possible um
and as far as the ethics goes while
there's a lot of nuance to it
i think the pie slice theorem is a
really good place to start
right which is and if we're
if we're going to be uh cutting
something in half and sharing it
generally the rule of thumb goes i cut
it in half and you pick or you cut it in
half and i pick but
not i cut it in half and then i pick
because then i'll i'll cut it unevenly
and take the big cell
right so the question is would would i
would i trade places and a part of an
ethical
relationship is that both sides are
benefit again a win-win
dynamic that we'd be happy to trade
places because we actually feel good
about
the experience of both sides of any
interaction so we have to say
when i think into the sentient
experience of this
animal and the way that i'm relating
with them
would i trade places and do i feel okay
about
my effect on their sentient experience
and
uh we could do a whole podcast to go
deeper but i think
asking that question earnestly is a
starting point i'd encourage for
everybody
yeah i i really i really appreciate that
perspective i was recently
on a podcast where someone was asking me
a very similar question
just my ethics around plant-based diets
and vegan and vegetarianism
and as he was talking two quotes came to
mind that really encapsulated my
general perspective one of them was the
ahimsa quote from the the aems
the eight limbs of yoga philosophy
and which is basically do no harm to
others and do no harm to our self and a
lot of times
that quote is actually taken out of
context it's just do no harm to others
but it also has followed up with do no
harm to ourselves
which i think is part of what you're
sharing is that there's a there's a
consideration
for loving others loving other creatures
and loving ourself
enough to make sure that we are covering
our bases making sure that we cover
our blind spots as a sustainable
biological
organism so we're healthy and vibrant
um and then the other quote that came up
for me
was by the the great alchemist
paracelsus
who said that everything is poison
everything is panacea it depends on
dosage
so that quote came up for me because i
said you know
if someone chooses to consume
meat and flesh products and animal
products that's their own
that's part of their own riddle you know
nutrition is largely a riddle
so you know i feel like a lot of it
really has to do with
dosage you know in terms of uh meat
products my personal philosophy is if
somebody is going to do that
let's make that a condiment instead of a
main course let's do it therapeutically
instead of with with gluttony
yeah i think
if if one factor is particularly the
first quote that you shared
and they say okay my goal is to
reduce unnecessary suffering and harm
to all life me and other life and to
optimize quality of life for me and all
other life
and then how do i make decisions aligned
with that
if i can be vibrantly healthy
on just plant matter and i have good
reason to believe that
less suffering happens as a result of
just eating plant matter than eating
plant
and animal matter because
more evolved complexity in animals than
in
plants nervous system you know more
capacity for
response also means more capacity for
sensing more capacity for pain for
suffering
and the animal was eating however many
plants they were
uh you know in terms of the agricultural
feed to get there in the first place so
you know if you bring up the argument
about what about the sanctions of plants
you've done more
plant damage by moving the plants
through animals so
it's a pretty easy argument to make if
if if one can
not eat animal products and do well
then it seems ethically
necessary to do so if one
does not know how to eat only plant
products
and do well and so where if they only
ate plant products they would be
suffering
and they would meaning they'd have uh
less
vital health or actual acute health
issues
and less capacity to do the things that
would then enrich quality of life for
others then it would be an ethical issue
not to but that doesn't automatically
mean carte blanche eat as much fat
refined meat as you want
there is a lack of nuance that i think
is pretty common where hardcore vegan is
an easy position
and i eat meat is an easy position
the point of view that says there are
times where i
feel that it's therapeutically relevant
to increase my key iron or my
animal proteins or whatever and i'm
gonna do the least amount of it
in the least evolved forms of life
um you know from the most humane
sourcing i can is very different than
just a carte blanche eight animals
right right
so i'm going to take this opportunity to
pivot
for the sake of time and um we've gone
down a few little rabbit holes which
have been cool
and i want to create the container
for the rest of this interview to dive
into
the qualia product and anything around
kind of this idea around neuro hacking
actually before we dive into the
particular product that you helped
formulate which i think
is absolutely brilliant and very
sophisticated which is why i wanted one
of the reasons i want to bring you on is
to
share the details of it um as we get
into that
can you share with us your interest in
quote unquote neuro
hacking as it's popularly called
yeah so neural hack for us
really means uh
optimizing neurologic function and
optimizing
mind brain interface capabilities so
we think of biohacking generally meaning
any way of
increasing function of the biologic
system and
you know biohacking could really just be
synonymous with
um good health care
and good well-being i think part of why
the term hacking has caught on and the
hacker ethos
is the hacker ethos was a little bit
counter authoritarianism right so
there's
authoritarianism in the medical
establishment process that
because of its inability to address
complex illness and the people that have
suffered from it while still having you
know uh
authorities hold a lot of rain on what
they think uh people shouldn't do
as well as its inability to you know
really help people optimize there's this
kind of
um the the hacking wasn't like
nature is the mainframe and we have to
hack it as we want to work with nature
but we're
we are working um around
establishment i think that's one of the
reasons that the term caught on another
idea was that somebody could hack a
computer system without understanding
all of the computer system they just had
to understand
ways of getting in which ended up
meaning a lot less information to still
have
a lot of capability so uh i think one of
the other ideas in biohacking
and consciousness hacking all those
terms was
uh the the least amount of input
necessary to create meaningful output
change
so that's i don't mean to interrupt but
i'm just glad you said it that way
because my pet peeve
is about the last the least amount of
effort to get the most amount of output
so i'm glad you phrased it that way
your pet peeve is thinking that way no
my pet peeve is
other people using the term hacking like
bio hacking or business hacking or
life hacking as a way to get as a way to
put in the least amount of
effort to get the most amount of results
and i think
you know i think tim ferriss kind of
maybe
did more than anybody at first to
popularize that idea
productivity hacking life hacking with
the four-hour work week and the idea of
hey can i
automate a lifestyle for myself with uh
you know
not as much time and then can i apply
that to body and other things and the
idea of the pareto principle of
there is a relatively small subset of
all the things one could do in a space
that can lead to much of the results of
the space and let's start there
it's a good principle now if there's 20
of the stuff you can do that will lead
to 80 of the results if you really care
about the area you're not happy with 80
of the results and so
you know when you think about just
increased
leverage right where less input can
create more output that doesn't
necessarily mean you continue to do
lessons but it might mean you just start
getting
exponentially more output because you
care more and you continue to invest a
lot with just higher leverage strategies
right so neural hacking
you know why it's interesting for us
what is interesting for
me is when i looked at all of the
dynamics in the world that we wanted to
affect at a macro level
looked at war and
religious differences and violence and
biodiversity loss and you know etc
it was pretty easy to see that
one of the common denominators across
all those issues in different sectors
was that they were all being mediated by
human behavior
and that in order to change any of them
we had to change human behavior
at scale and that all the solutions we
needed were going to be brought about by
human behavior
or they weren't right and so
what are all the things that influence
human behavior to
directly cause harm to indirectly
externalize harm
to uh work on solutions to work on
solutions effectively
right like what are all the things that
influence those capacities and those
predispositions
well it's the social systems do
economics and what you incentivize
has a huge effect the environment and
the environmental psychology influences
have a huge effect
our psychology our worldview our
definition of success
definition of self another has a huge
effect you know our trauma
all like that but our physiology has a
huge effect
and that was the part that we want to
address here uh we're used to thinking
of kind of a nature nurture divide where
nature is assumed to mean something like
genetics
and it's fairly unchangeable and
nurture equals other stuff but this is a
this is
of course very outdated way of thinking
about it um
are genetics mostly selected for
neuroplasticity
we don't run fast like cheetahs we don't
fly like birds we don't swim very well
like fish we don't really have
many special capacities that are
physiologically built in but we can make
tools that do any of those things better
than specialists
right we can again with our tools go
faster than cheetahs fly faster than
birds go deeper underwater than whales
etc the strings of a gorilla is nothing
compared to that of a hydraulic press
and so we selected for the capacity to
do abstraction and develop tools and
extend ourselves to those tools but that
tools those tools meant we were going to
change our environment rapidly which
meant
if we had fixed wiring when we were
adapted to our evolutionary environment
we would be unadapted to the new worlds
that we'd create so we had to
have very little hardwiring so that we
could softwire to the new environments
we
creating which is why we're pretty much
useless for the first year of our life
compared to a gorilla that can do stuff
in the first five minutes a horse that's
up and walking in the first few minutes
is because we're born very neonos
we have a very long developmental period
because rather than have hardwired
behaviors we have
uh radical plasticity for firm wiring
what is going to be adaptive to the
environment that we're born into and
then we have continued neuroplasticity
throughout life so basically evolution
said
only being able to change our behavior
through natural selection through
breeding over a long period of time is
very slow
so we're evolving a creature that can
change its behavior radically just by
software updates
mimetics right which are mediated by you
know
neural coding and you know
neuroplasticity
so genetics are genetics selected for
mimetics
so rather than having genetic
predispositions for really good or
really shitty behavior we have genetic
predispositions to be memetically
susceptible to whatever our conditioning
is
um and so mostly we're looking at
conditioning
but and i'm stating that to say
the idea that we have evolutionary
biology predispositions that just
inexorably suck
i don't believe is well supported
but we can say that physiology uh
does affect patterns of human experience
and human behavior not even so much at
the level of genetics we could get into
that but at the level of just whether or
not the physiology is in tune
right so if hormones are out of balance
life is very different than if they're
in balance brain chemistry is out of
balance
it's very different and so almost
everyone has experienced their
physiology
being out of balance in ways that
affected their psyche affected their
emotions
affected their cognition and you're
going to think of it as
when an instrument is out of tune you
kind of can't play anything
on it no matter if you know how to play
well or not
it sounds good so before we look at
upgrading our system right
making them get our guitar a better
guitar we just look at getting it in
tune first
we see there's a tremendous amount of
predisposition
for shitty behavior that is actually
untuned physiologies
that is neurochemical imbalances
hormonal imbalances
microbiome imbalances etc that lead to
less system resilience less emotional
resilience
less impulse control because when you
think about
things we care about psychologically
empathy perspective taking
complex thinking problem solving
impulse control etc those are all
mediated over certain neural circuits
involving certain neurochemistry and
those can be physiologically up or down
regulated
so neural hacking was interesting for us
to say how can we
take a more complex approach to how we
address
tuning the organism complex system
science multifactorial etc
so that we can both decrease unnecessary
suffering
at the human level increase quality of
life at the human level but also
increase the capacity for and
predisposition for
that human becoming uh
an asset on nature's balance sheet
rather than liability
and how does how does qualia fit into
that
yeah so quality is the first product
that we have actually
brought to market that's for sale we
have quite a few other products both
additional versions of quality and
completely different products with
different goals that are
in various phases of development and
will come out
soon uh the reason why we started with
qualia is
uh one
it was it's a familiar delivery
mechanism
taking pills is much more familiar to
people uh
than strapping on eeg units or using
transcranial stimulation so there's a
low barrier to entry in terms of
familiarity
there's also a low barrier to entry in
terms of it takes
it doesn't take very much will there's
not much behavioral
uh involved in pigment pill and
that it has the capacity to not only
have the effect that it has but it has
the effect of
increasing one's capacity to do the
other things that are harder to do
because of
its effect on uh motivational chemistry
and so uh those were all reasons why we
saw it as a
as a meaningful starting place um and
then
the desire to be productive is high for
everyone the demand
is high from you know just your life and
dealing with shit and economics point of
view and from the point of view of if
you're tuned into the world scenario and
you realize how much needs to
happen there's a major demand to be you
know creative and
productive in shifting things uh
well we have more challenges to
attention span from
more distractions and so we see
increased you know maybe not in your
audience but we
in in wide audiences increase adderall
use increased
smart brain five hour energy etc your
group is probably doing adaptogens
um but uh
we wanted to see if we could make
something that had a much
wider set of positive effects than
those single molecule solutions had and
that had lastingly positive rather than
lastingly negative effects because
you know single molecule pharmacological
usually psychostimulants will have an
effect but it's usually quite narrow
right your adderall is going to affect
presynaptic
dopamine increase it's going to increase
focus and concentration
and drive but it's going to decrease
uh task switching working memory
and oftentimes empathy um
and then it's gonna override
your and imbalance your own endogenous
dopamine regulatory system which leads
to down regulation independence we
wanted to see could we
increase concentration and focus so you
could be highly focused
while increasing task switching so you
could move between tasks as needed
better simultaneously
while increasing long-term memory
short-term memory working memory speed
of memory
and increasing analytic capability and
synthetic capability simultaneously
etc so how do we increase
the capacity of all of those meaningful
subjective experiences and cognitive
capacities that go into creative
productive flow states where
where uh you know cognition is uh fully
available accessible
and um that's to start by just kind of
modeling what are all the capacities and
states
that are desired and then we model what
what are the underlying physiologic
mechanisms that mediate each of those
what are the chemistries that affect
those mechanisms
and then what are the chemistries that
are generally well tolerated
whose effect on other systems is also
positive and where we get positive
synergies between
the chemistries and then that was the
beginning of our formulation process
and then you know many many cycles of
iteration to get to where it is
and what what are what are some of the
the effects that you've seen across the
board with people i mean i could easily
give my experience but i'm i'm about a
month into it right now
and i'm just curious from your your
perspective
as the core formulator and also
receiving testimonials from other people
and also doing it yourself i'm curious
like what what across the board do you
see is the most common
um enhancements or effects
so first uh i will
say for this podcast you know our
necessary
medical disclaimer um of course
we are not uh able to prescribe treat
diagnose anything
quality shouldn't be used for any
medical conditions if you have medical
conditions like
psychiatric conditions go to your health
care professional
and that neither ronnie or his company
or neurohacker et cetera should be taken
for medical advice
all of that's a given and we can't make
any claims because we haven't done
uh the kind of fda approval
trials that are necessary to be able to
make claims so i can't say quality does
anything
um i can tell you what we intended and i
can tell you
things that people have reported so as
far as
people have reported um
increased total working memory how many
things they can simultaneously hold and
actually make good sense of
increased rate of memory their verbal
fluency going up so rather than the word
on the tip of their tongue and they feel
like they can't
catch it that they actually have
you know meaningfully increased verbal
fluency and flow
increased creativity epiphany insight
increased pattern recognition and also
kind of error recognition um you know
all of those things we've heard
uh a lot uh
increased emotional resilience and drive
both for the things they really love
right things that people are motivated
to do where they can actually
stay on task for a much longer period of
time and even in the face of setbacks
continue to feel good and
continue but also things that people
would normally procrastinate
actually feeling like they can focus on
and get done without being bothered by
them so
we didn't expect that we've had so many
people write saying that
they actually did their taxes and
cleaned their desk and finish their
papers
because rather than it being an odious
process they were able to just focus and
and not have any drama about it so good
about it
decreased internal sense of drama was
also one of the things
which doesn't mean emotional blunting
people still said they
you know would cry at inspiring things
and feel happy and grateful and feel sad
when there was something
real to feel sad about but they were
making up less stories because they were
just thinking
so the bullshit thinking that led to a
bunch of emotional reactions about what
isn't real
decreased um and
uh increased vividness of dreams lucid
dreams
now there's a lot of people that have
claimed things for their medical
conditions people with
you know many interesting medical
conditions have said
that their conditions were meaningfully
decreased or gone but
again that's way outside the scope of
anything we're allowed to
talk about um and
you know it's important to say we didn't
make quality up to
uh cure conditions we did make it for
well people who are seeking optimization
where
this would have a
wider scope of optimization than other
solutions that were available
and with less long-term negatives and
hopefully even long-term positives and
for people who have been
using uh the product for a long time and
then used it
and stopped taking it for a while and
tracked their baseline
the report of long-term positives has
continued
that is a really important distinction
isn't it because typically
in a supplement um it is
it is something that we have to continue
to take
in order to derive the effects however
in something like this the the
i guess the intention or maybe just the
side effect that has been noticed is
that even when somebody stops taking it
their baseline resilience or their
baseline
cognition elevates to a new level where
they don't have to keep taking it yet
they're better off for
taking it yeah and again we don't have
the kind of research where we can
quantify that yet though we're in the
early stages of gathering it
um and we will have that you know in the
not too distant future we're really
excited about it
but in a dynamic system where you
continue to have
lots of system inputs we don't expect
any effect to be
you know permanent just like exercise
isn't meditation isn't someone to
meditate for a bunch of years and if
they stop they can start getting more
stressed out
but as much of an effect as if someone
has exercise they have really good
fitness
a few months later they're still in
different shape than someone who didn't
exercise
we were looking for a similar effect to
that which is if you have an upregulated
system
uh there should be continuance of that
up regulation
until there is you know too much that is
uh
down regulating it and it doesn't have
continued support right
through a couple mechanisms our
intention was that if people were
operating at increased efficiency
continuously over a long period of time
that there would be
actual new rewiring neuroplastic
rewiring
along that state as baseline and
that we have a lot of chemistry that's
focused on supporting
endogenous processes of neurogenesis and
synaptogenesis
so neural structuring processes so you
don't feel those right away the things
that you feel right away are things that
are affecting neurotransmission
but for longer term effects we looked at
specifically chemicals that support
development of new synaptic structures
new
new you know neurite formation and new
progenitor stem cell neuron formation
differentiation
so that those endogenous processes could
happen in an upregulated fashion
and that's where you could get not just
chemical changes but structural changes
where the structural changes
uh you know would have the capacity to
be
more enduring
yeah there's a my my brain just went in
a whole bunch of different directions
um however we don't have time for that
too
so whoo okay so with all that said and i
think that's an
i think we've already taken a huge we've
taken everybody on
a few different rabbit holes into some
very um
some very in-depth territory and
especially this last part and i just
want to i just want to
maybe add to this in and if if
anybody if anything went over anyone's
head i really
invite everybody to continue to research
maybe continue to listen to this
interview and listen to some of the
daniel's other interviews
and content free content on youtube
because
this man is obviously what i would call
a polymath which is
um one of my colleagues john d martini
who i had on the show recently
he's obviously one and it's basically
somebody who has gained a certain level
of
mastery in multiple disciplines
and which is one of the reasons not only
you fascinate me so much because that's
something
i'm trying to optimize within myself
because i have so many interests
but it's just something that i have a
great deal of respect for because
i know the type of work and devotion
to your craft it takes to really
to really weed through all the
distinctions and nuances to be able to
critically think
and extrapolate information the way that
you do so for everyone listening
um you just continue to investigate
these things
and i really encourage everybody to
actually go to
your website daniel which i'll let you
tell everybody about which has a lot
more
broken down research and information on
the concepts that you're talking about
and on the qualia product what is that
website
neurohacker.com
cool so they can go to neurohacker.com i
believe that you guys
also have a monthly subscription for
people that want to test it over a
longer term
you do cool
and uh is there any any more information
or anything you'd love to leave the
audience off with at this point
uh just that it was a delight and honor
to
be here with you and i appreciate the
work you were doing and
uh sharing good resources with people
educating people and
happy about the friendship and to
continue and evolve it
and if there are future topics that are
interesting that we can share about i'd
be
very happy to absolutely well i'm glad
you said that because i got a whole
bunch of them for you and i would love
to have you back on the show whenever
you'd like to be on
sounds great okay awesome
yeah thank you so much for joining me
and thank all of you
as always for tuning in to at this point
the holistic health and human potential
show
i am your host ronnie landis and
this has been another phenomenal episode
with a phenomenal guest i hope you guys
appreciated it
and i hope you take at least one two or
three key nuggets of insight
that will help you really push the
boundaries of your own human potential
thank you so much for joining us